to putting aside the definition of
depression the if you just focus on how
to not overcome it the necessary basis
would be to recognize that first and
foremost depression is not caused by
anything external to you there might be
external reasons but depression it's
more of a state of mind in regard to the
those reasons in regard to those things
that seemingly are the ones making us
depressed so and this is true for any
unpleasant feeling any unpleasant mental
state and it's it's a natural tendency
to assume that it's it's the world and
it's the things in the world that
righteously upset us or other factors
caused emotional responses and so on
including depression as a mental state
but if they were truly the case then
freedom from anything unpleasant would
not be possible it wouldn't be possible
to feel some from suffering or any kind
which includes depression as well
because if it were truly rooted in
external circumstances in in in in
basically in your environment you can't
control that and above all like even
even if you could control now you can't
control what happen in the past
obviously and you certainly can't
control what's going to happen in the
future so if the attitude is still that
it's the the environments responsibility
the the reason is the environment and
I'm subjected to this depression or any
other mental state there won't be any
recruiting with depression unless their
data to changes so it can be slightly
like you know slightly unpleasant to to
admit that because then immediately
people would jump onto the assumption
also what is it my fault nobody nobody
talks about fault but we talk about
responsibility so it is your
responsibility to give in or to not give
in
to the feelings that have been caused by
the world and the reason what is your
responsibility it's because none of the
none of the things you do on account of
your feelings are actually can actually
be rooted in those feelings and by that
I mean that the world say your
experience of this with that too makes
you feel good or bad
pleasantly unpleasantly and that's it
that's the experience in itself but it's
the ignorant mind the mind that hasn't
been trained hasn't been restrained that
when it's touched by pleasure it will
want more of it automatically it's not a
rational sort of premeditated decision
so agreeable things come to me and the
mind automatically jumps on it and
that's the result of an unrestrained
mind that has been they still under the
influence of ignorance likewise when
there is the unpleasant experience
coming my way the unrestrained mind
under the influence of ignorance will
automatically resist it trying to get
rid of it try to prevent it from
happening and that's that's basically
fighting the battle on a completely
wrong ground and and you will maintain
the wrong ground for as long as you
maintain the gratuitous desire to avoid
sensual pleasures so as long as you
maintain the gratuitous craving towards
Pleasant feeling because of that you're
also maintaining the gratuitous
resistance to the unpleasant feeling so
depression being one of the profound
unpleasant feelings or unpleasant states
of mind that have been sort of developed
over a period of time it's something
that you have to stop regarding it as
being rooted in the world even if the
world was very unjust and things happen
to you that they're now making you
righteously depressed so to speak you
don't need to be the victim of the
depression so as a mental state of
depression or any other unpleasant state
as I said
the problem of it is not in what
happened or why you you you have
depressed so or all these things that
that seemingly revolve around it the
problem is you suffer you suffer on
account of it that's the sole issue
because if say depression wasn't felt
unpleasantly you wouldn't suffer it
wouldn't be a problem so you want to
recognize where your responsibility lies
not in the fact that you were
experiencing depression or any other
adverse state of the mind but in the
fact that you are responsible for
resisting unpleasant experience and you
will remain resisting it for as long as
you're equally indulging pleasant
experience won't implies annex building
in the prospect of pleasant experience
that's why in the Buddhist teaching the
sense restraint needs to come first you
need to start saying no to gratuitous
indulgence of pleasures of unrestrained
speech careless speech lapsing in your
mindfulness and so on if you start
restraining that you'll get to
understand then that well you get to see
where the line is you get to see what
has been caused by the world and then
you get to see the responsibility for
your own reaction towards it and in that
sense whatever it's depressing you even
if there is not a specific reason if you
just feel numb and depressed for
whatever reason the point is it's
unpleasant if you stop resisting the
displeasure of it depression can have no
hold over you and same goes for anxiety
singles for any other state but in order
to get to that point where you can see
that it's that it's up to you to
maintain the line which these phenomena
cannot cross in order to get there you
need to start restraining yourself in
regard to things that you can actually
control such as how much you how much
you eat for sensuality how much we talk
out of the reason sensuality gossip and
so on whether you keep the precepts
whether you live restrain by the virtue
because if your body is leaking out all
these unwholesome behaviors you can't
expect them to have any control over
your mind which is the root for these
behaviors so first you need to stop the
outlets of the wrong behaviors
and that's why it's the winner kept
talking about the training and he trains
himself thus and who you need to keep
keep repeating it it's not like a
decision determination that you make
make today and then automatically it
will be held for the rest of your life
no it's just something to keep going
back to and drilling it and drilling it
and drilling it and drilling it like any
other form of training so that's where
you train in regard to so that you can
get to see that it's your own attitude
in regard to what you're currently
feeling that's the root of depression
anxiety that's the root of sensuality
for the matter as well
careless desires and so on and if you
just deal with it on that level you
won't have to worry about the world at
all because you'll know if the world
affects you positively or negatively it
will have to do so through this gateway
the Gateway of your attitude toward your
own feelings not your attitude towards
him or her or or what they say or what
happened my past my future my planned my
anxieties no it's only what I'm feeling
presently that's where your attitude
matters if you're presently resisting it
you will suffer if you're presently
indulging it you will suffer if your
palet presently careless about it you
will also suffer so undoing the views
that put the put the responsibility or
the blame sometimes on the world and
circumstances not putting the blame on
yourself either by recognizing that the
state of affairs is such that if you are
careless in regard to the presently
enduring feeling in your experience you
will be victim then to your mental
states if you learn how to train
yourself and not deny the mental states
not blame the world but recognize when
there is agreeable feeling hold yourself
back a bit don't just go for for the
pleasure that's offered and and believe
that everything else will disappear as a
result of joy that's going to replace it
when there is an unpleasant feeling then
you will equally have strength to then
not sink in it either because you've
been pretty much learning how to how to
swim and when there's an either Pleasant
or unpleasant feeling you will be able
to not give in to careless distraction
and sort of mindless attitude so to
speak so so that's that's pretty much in
brief in the nutshell how you should be
doing with any dealing with any
unpleasant mental state don't try to get
rid of it don't blame the world
recognize the unpleasantness of it and
stop resisting the unpleasantness of it
in order to be able to stop resisting
the unpleasantness of of that mental
state you must develop yourself in
regard to Pleasant mental states as well
so you can't just have it pleasure
and when this pleasure comes you have
all control over it no in order to be
able to not be affected by unpleasant
feelings you have to be restraining
yourself in regard to pleasant feelings
and that's why it in a way already you
get to discern the principle of the
middle way is it like even even it
doesn't necessarily mean I'll just be
moderate you have to also recognize like
moderate it's not a fixed thing but
moderate for someone it's extreme for
someone else so it's not about
moderation necessarily it's more about
recognition whether your attitude is
rooted in sensuality whether it's rooted
in your will
whether it's rooted in caelis behavior
whether it's rooted in non careless
behavior how how that manifests
practically that varies but you don't
need to worry about am i moderate enough
am I am I saying no enough you have to
worry about where your intentions are
rooted in regard to your own feelings so
so that's why it's not it's not just
it's not as easy just just moderate just
tone down your behavior and you'll be
happy no because as I said what's toned
down for somebody somebody it isn't for
somebody else it all depends where your
motivation is rooted if your motivation
is rooted in carelessly indulging
pleasurable experiences of any kind
carelessly indulging a sense of taste
sensuality visual bodily you will have
no say then when these experiences
changes you will have no say and you
will have no other option but to then
resist it because that's the attitude
you've been cultivating overdoing it
when there is a pleasure you overdo
towards it when there is an pain
you overdo trying to get rid of it so if
if that attitude began if that kind of
training starts to be implemented then
any like long lasting persisting mental
states will will start to fade away
because they do require a constant fuel
they do require maintenance and now you
stop maintaining it through these
ignorant attitudes and that's how ok as
I said whatever whatever the issues of
the psychological nature might be
bothering you if your behavior is being
kept in check then you get to recognize
your responsibility for your own
attitude towards your own feelings and
then none of these states no matter how
long they've been can exercise any
influence over you because the Gateway
for any influence over your positive or
negative is through your attitude you're
opening toward your own feelings